A Finding Aid to the Kevin MacDonald papers, 1958-2006, in the Archives of American Art AAA.macdkevi
Archives of American Art
Kevin MacDonald papers
1958-2006
AAA.macdkevi
Archives of American Art
7.7 Linear feet
The papers of Washington, D.C. painter and printmaker Kevin MacDonald measure 7.7 linear feet, and date from 1958-2006. The collection contains correspondence with friends and colleagues; journals, notebooks, and other writings; printed material; artwork by MacDonald and others; 29 sketchbooks; and sound, video, and film recordings. Of note are several files regarding his work with the Washington Project for the Arts.
MacDonald, Kevin
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. research facility. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of Washington, D.C. painter and printmaker Kevin MacDonald measure 7.7 linear feet, and date from 1958-2006. The collection contains correspondence with friends and colleagues; journals, notebooks, and other writings; printed material; artwork by MacDonald and others; 29 sketchbooks; and sound, video, and film recordings. Of note are several files regarding his work with the Washington Project for the Arts.
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged as 8 series.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1968-2006 (1.9 linear feet:; Boxes 1-2)
Series 2: Notebooks and Journals, 1968-2005 (1.3 linear feet; Boxes 2-4)
Series 3: Writings, 1970s-1999 (0.3 linear feet; Box 4)
Series 4: Project Files, 1958-2005 (1.1 linear feet; Boxes 4-5, 9)
Series 5: Printed Material, circa 1970-2004 (1.0 linear foot; Boxes 5-6, 9)
Series 6: Artwork, 1960s-2000s (0.5 linear feet; Boxes 6, 9)
Series 7: Sketchbooks, circa 1969-2006 (1.1 linear feet; Boxes 6-7, 9)
Series 8: Sound, Video, and Film Recordings, circa 1970s-1990s (0.5 linear feet; Boxes 7-8)
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated in 2012 by Robin Moore, Kevin MacDonald's widow.
Biographical/Historical note
Kevin MacDonald (1946-2006) was a painter and printmaker in Washington, D.C. He received a BFA from George Washington University in 1969, and also took courses at the Corcoran Gallery of Art. From 1967 to 1977 he worked at the Phillips Collection. After leaving the Phillips he worked full-time as an artist, taking an active role in the D.C. arts community. He was co-curator of “The Washington Show” at the Corcoran Gallery of Art in 1986, and served on the Board of Directors for both the Washington Project for the Arts (1986-1992) and Washington Area Lawyers for the Arts (1991-1997). MacDonald regularly exhibited his work at the Lunn Gallery and David Adamson Gallery, and had artist residencies at the Virginia Center for the Creative Arts (1995) and Oglebay Institute (1993). MacDonald also had an interest in music, and served as art director of a short-lived music fanzine called “Infiltrator.” He was in Twisted Teenage Plot, a band organized by fellow artist Michael Clark, and worked with artist and musician Robin Rose on a collaboration called “Scriptronics.” He lived most of his life in Silver Spring, Maryland, a suburb of D.C., and was married to art consultant Robin Moore.
Washington Project for the Arts, (D.C.); Diaries; Motion pictures (visual works); Notebooks; Painters--Washington (D.C.); Printmakers--Washington (D.C.); Sketchbooks; Sound recordings; Video recordings
- Correspondence, 1968-2006; Series 1; 1.9 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence, mostly of a personal nature, is with friends and fellow artists. Included are many handmade holiday and greeting cards, mail art, and illustrated letters. Much of MacDonald's correspondence with friends extends over two decades or more. Of note is correspondence with artists Wilfred Brunner, Michael Clark, Don Cook, Joe Holbach, Susan Kaprov, and Dana Zed.
  - A, Miscellaneous, 1987-2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bisese, Eddie and Liza Kirwin, 1992-2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bodnarchuk, Raya, 1983-1996 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brunner, Wilfred and Joyce Jewell, circa 1976-1997 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - B, Miscellaneous, 1988-2001 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chavanat, Damien, 1992-2001 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clark, Michael, 1974-2003; undated (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Cook, Don, circa 1980s-2004 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - C, Miscellaneous, 1981-2005 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - D, Miscellaneous, 1975-2006 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - F, Miscellaneous, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - G, Miscellaneous, 1977-2006 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Holbach, Joe, circa 1974-1998 (Box 1, Folder 15-19)
  - H, Miscellaneous, 1981-2006 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - J-K, Miscellaneous, 1984-1988; 2005 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Kaprov, Susan, 1971-2000 (Box 1, Folder 22-29)
  - Leary, Mary, 1977-1999 (Box 1, Folder 30-33)
  - Littlefield, Cynthia, 1988-1996 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - L, Miscellaneous, 1982; circa 2002 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - M, Miscellaneous, 1977-circa 2000 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Nelson, Cathie France, circa 1968-1984 (Box 1, Folder 37-40)
  - Nelson, Cathie France, 1985-1990 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Nelson, Cathie France, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - N-R, Miscellaneous, 1978-2001 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Stahlhuth, Harold Val, 1975-1979 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - S, Miscellaneous, circa 1986-2004 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - W, Miscellaneous, 1976-2000 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Yelloz, Catherine, 1994-2002 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Zed, Dana Smith, 1980-2005 (Box 2, Folder 8-21)
  - Zimmerman, Peter, 1982-2005 (Box 2, Folder 22-25)
  - Outgoing Letters (Copies), 2004; 1971-1999 (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
  - First Names Only and Unidentified, circa 1976-2006 (Box 2, Folder 28-29)
- Notebooks and Journals, 1968-2005; Series 2; 1.3 Linear feet Boxes 2-4
  Journals and notebooks contain various writings by Kevin MacDonald. Journals mostly include dated entries containing thoughts on his life and art. Some poetry is also included. Other notebooks contain poetry, travel logs, ideas and sketchs for artwork, and thoughts on art.
  Arrangement note
  Journals are arranged in chronological order followed by titled notebooks. Other notebooks are arranged in rough chronological order at the end of the series.
  - Journal, 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Journal, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Journal, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Journal, 1972-1976 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Journal, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Journal, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Journal, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Journal, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Journal, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Journal, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Journal, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Journal, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Journal, 1982-1984 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Journal, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Journal, 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Journal, 1988-1991 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Journal, 1991-2005 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Notebook, "Four (4) Short Poems", undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Notebook, "Frances and Kevin in New Mexico", 2000 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Notebook, "Idea & Workbook", 1982-1987 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Notebook, "Idea & Workbook", 1987-1994 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Notebook, "Idea & Workbook", 1994-2001 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Notebook, Income and Expenses, 1974-1980 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Notebook, "Travel Book", circa 1977-1982 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Notebook, "Travel Book", 1982-1995 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Notebook, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Notebook, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Notebook, circa 1970 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Notebook, circa 1971 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Notebook, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Notebook, circa 1994 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Notebook, circa 2000-2005 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Notebook, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Notebook, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Writings, 1970s-1999; Series 3; 0.3 Linear feet Box 4
  Writings are by Kevin MacDonald and others. MacDonalds writings include many notes on art and philosophy, performance ideas, song lyrics and poetry. Also found are a few draft essays and talks. Writings by others include poetry and creative writing pieces.
  - Essay, "The Washington Show", circa 1985 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Writings, 1970s (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Notes, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Notes on I-Ching and Tarot, circa 1983-1994 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Notes on Painting, circa 1980s (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Notes on Philosophy and Creativity, circa 1980s (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Performance Ideas, circa 1980s-1993 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Poetry, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Song Lyrics, circa 1980-1985 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Talk, "Bringing Art Home: Surviving Outside of New York", undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Talk on Carroll Sockwell, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Writings on Lewes, Delaware, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - "Pictures From Seurat," Poems by Bob Wickless, circa 1994 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Writings by Joe Holbach, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Writings by Others, 1977-1980s (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Project Files, 1958-2005; Series 4; 1.1 Linear feet Boxes 4-5, 9
  Found here are Kevin MacDonald's files regarding his various projects as a professional artist. Included are files on project ideas, research, proposals, commissions, artist-in-residence, and exhibitions. Of note are his files on the Washington Project for the Arts, for which he served on the Board of Directors, and exhibition files for "The Washington Show," which he co-curated at the Corcoran Gallery of Art.
  - Artist-in-Residence, Wheeling, West Virginia, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Bookworks, 1986-1991 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Corcoran Gallery of Art, 1980-1982 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Dinner at Herbs, circa 1990 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Don Cook Projects and Proposals, circa 1989-1996 (Box 4, Folder 27-28)
  - Emblemata du Coeur, undated (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Exhibition, "Public Space/Public Place", circa 1980-1995 (Box 4, Folder 30-31)
  - Exhibition, "The Washington Show", 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 32-35)
  - Exhibition Installation Photographs, circa 1982 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Faces of the Fallen Memorial, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Infiltrator Magazine, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - History of Silver Spring, 1958-2003 (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
  - Montgomery College Teaching Records, circa 1999 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Mythology and Celtic History, circa 1971-1990s (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Patti Smith Fan Club, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - "Physics" Performance and Book, circa 1993 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Project Ideas and Proposals, circa 1991-2005 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Research, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Source Photographs and Images, circa 1990s (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Washington Area Lawyers for the Arts, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Washington Project for the Arts, 1986-1992 (Box 5, Folder 13-17)
    Oversized material housed in Box 9, Folder 2
  - Washington Project for the Arts, Botswana, circa 1986-1988 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Washington Project for the Arts, Cabaret Re-Voltaire, 1992; Includes 1 videocassette (VHS) (Box 5, Folder 19-20)
  - Oversized, Washington Circle Gallery of Fine Art, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Oversized, Washington Project for the Arts, from Box 5, Folder 13, circa 1981 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Printed Material, circa 1970-2004; Series 5; 1 Linear feet Boxes 5-6, 9
  Printed material includes exhibition catalogs, announcements, and invitiations, as well as magazines and news clippings about MacDonald and other Washington, D.C. artists. Additionally, there are several zines and photocopied event flyers containing artwork by MacDonald. Also of note is a published booklet about the experimental music and art collaboration between Kevin MacDonald and Robin Rose called "Scriptronics."
  - Booklet, "Scriptronics", circa 1981 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Event Flyers, 1980s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Invitations, circa 1976-2004 (Box 5, Folder 23-25)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, circa 1974-2002 (Box 5, Folder 26-28)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, circa 1978-2002 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Magazines, 1981-2000 (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
    Oversized material housed in Box 9, Folder 3
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, circa 1970-1992 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - News Clippings, 1982-2002 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - News Clippings regarding Physics, circa 1996-2003 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Newsletters, circa 2000 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Zine, 11th Street Ruse, circa 1992-1996 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Zine, Abortion, circa 1978-1980 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Zine, Infiltrator, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    Oversized material housed in Box 9, Folder 4
  - Zines, Miscellaneous, 1980-1981 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Oversized Magazine, Washington Review, from Box 6, Folder 2, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Zine, Infiltrator, from Box 6, Folder 10, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Artwork, 1960s-2000s; Series 6; 0.5 Linear feet Boxes 6, 9
  Artwork by Kevin MacDonald includes drawings and paintings used as preliminary studies for finished works, handmade Christmas cards, collages, "xerox books," and original collages that were used for event flyers. Also found is one paintbrush belonging to MacDonald. Additionally there are collages, art books, and watercolors by other artists including friend Joe Holbach.
  - Book Illustrations, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Christmas and Greeting Cards, circa 1970s-2000s (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Collages, circa 1979 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    Oversized material housed in Box 9, Folder 5
  - Color Studies, circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 15-16)
  - Drawings, circa 1960s-1970s; undated (Box 6, Folder 17-18)
  - Drawings and Paintings, circa 1970s; undated (Box 6, Folder 19-20)
    Oversized material housed in Box 9, Folder 6
  - Drawings for Brandeis Art Exhibit, undated (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Oil Pastel Drawings, undated (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Original Flyers (Collage), 1970s-1980s (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Paintbrush, undated (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Xerox Books, 1975-1990 (Box 6, Folder 25-26)
  - Xerox Book Pages and Collages, 1970s-1990s (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Joe Holbach, "Last Call", 1982 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Joe Holbach, Xerox Books, undated; 1991 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Unidentifed Artist, Handmade Book, undated (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Artwork by Others, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 6, Folder 31)
    Oversized material housed in Box 9, Folder 7
  - Oversized Collages, from Box 6, Folder 14, circa 1994 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Oversized Drawings and Paintings, from Box 6, Folder 19, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Oversized Artwork by Others, from Box 6, Folder 31, 1975-1981 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Sketchbooks, circa 1969-2006; Series 7; 1.1 Linear feet Boxes 6-7, 9
  Twenty-nine sketchbooks belonging to Kevin MacDonald depict preliminary ideas and studies for finished works. Sketches are in pencil, ink, colored pencil, watercolor, and pastel.
  - Sketchbooks, undated (Box 6, Folder 32-34)
  - Sketchbooks, undated (Box 7, Folder 1-11)
  - Sketchbook, circa 1969 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Sketchbook, 1970-1975 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Sketchbook, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Sketchbook, 1988-1990 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Sketchbook, 1990-1993 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Sketchbook, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Sketchbook, 2000s (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Sketchbook, 2006 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Oversized Sketchbooks, undated (Box 9, Folder 8-9)
  - Oversized Sketchbook, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Sound, Video, and Film Recordings, circa 1970s-1990s; Series 8; 0.5 Linear feet Boxes 7-8
  Found here is one videocassette containing two interviews with Kevin MacDonald. Also found are 14 sound cassettes containing music by Kevin MacDonald and others. Of note is a cassette containing recordings of MacDonald's band Twisted Teenage Plot and a live recording of Scriptronics, his experimental music collaboration with artist Robin Rose. Additionally, there are three unidentified Super 8 mm film reels.
  - Interviews with Kevin MacDonald, undated; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - "Dana - I Wish You Could Hear the Piano", 1980s; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 8, Item 1)
    Cassette label lists music by Brian Eno and David Byrne, selections from Teenage Jesus and the Jerks and DNA, and four untitled compositions by Michael [illegible] and Dale Scott
  - Frankel MacDonald Rose, Patti Smith "Live In London", circa 1976; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 8, Item 2)
  - Ilab, undated; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 8, Item 3)
  - Kevin & Judith: String Duo, undated; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 8, Item 4)
  - LA Conversation, undated; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 8, Item 5)
  - Rose/Clark/MacDonald, 1981; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 8, Item 6)
  - Russolo's Revenge, undated; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 8, Item 7)
  - Scriptronics Live: New Music America, Scriptronics Sampler, 1980s; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 8, Item 8)
  - Spontaneous Human Combustion, undated; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 8, Item 9)
  - Solemn French Choirboys, "This is the Order", undated; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 8, Item 10)
  - Twisted Teenage Plot, 1980s; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 8, Item 11)
  - Urban Verbs, undated; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 8, Item 12)
  - Urban Verbs at Cellar Door 2/28/79, Blondie, John Lennon, 1979; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 8, Item 13)
  - Urban Verbs at Corcoran Ball, 1978; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 8, Item 14)
  - Unidentified Recordings, undated; 3 Film reels (Box 8, Item 15-17)